we have our second keynote speaker
Professor Jason adame
so Jason is the 2002 professorial chair
in the sociology of education at the
University of Cambridge the youngest
professor at the moment
and previously Jason was professor of
Sociology in the school of education at
the College of social sciences
um he's also held the position of
associate professor in sociology at
Durham University and Deputy executive
Dean for people and culture in the
faculty of social science and health
Jason is a visiting professor at Ohio
State University in the office of
diversity and inclusion and an honorary
professor at the universities of Durham
in Glasgow dressing holds other visiting
professorships a Coventry University
of Northampton and Nelson Mandela
University he's a trustee of the running
mate trust the UK's leading race
equality Think Tank
um and the British sociological
Association
so Jason sits on the center for labor
the social studies the national advisory
panel and the NHS race and health
Observatory academic reference group
and he's a fellow of the Royal Society
of Arts so shall we welcome Professor
Jason
yeah what about you Jason
oh thank you so so much
um so good to see you again as well
um
how is life treating everyone I can't
see anybody so um I don't sorry that
you've seen my silly face from the
screen but how are your keeping is
everyone well
I can't tell so I'm hoping everyone is
wrong this is good thank you Kate
um and and thanks everyone else
brilliant
um oh it's brilliant doing great this is
really good I just wanted to say like um
it's such an honor to be here with all
of you um it's honestly it's such a big
privilege it really means a hell of a
lot and I mean before I say anything
lots of any no um I'm more
motivated to learn from all of you
um so I won't be speaking for too long I
also know that we're slightly behind
schedule as well so I kind of really
want to engage with all of you and I
just want to say um
you know
I was very fortunate about how many
years might be six or seven years ago
now I feel like it's seven years ago so
I I went to the first one of these
and um I was I was fortunate enough
um that a a wonderful
exceptional human being who happens to
be one of the best academics on the
planet Dr Bernadine took a chance on me
and put me on the stage with at the time
um Professor
um Palmer and Professor Chilean
and Professor Donald Palmer even and
Professor Robbie and and gave me an
opportunity
um at King's College
um back then and that that moment ended
up proving to be one of those seminal
moments of my life so it's so crazy to
see this thing kind of come full circle
in terms of you know Harold benedine has
built this community and how it's going
on to thrive and go to where it's gone
to now and never did I think in a
million years
um that I would uh ever be headlining
any kind of bill because I was just so
grateful that uh Bernadine saw something
to me and had me involved in the first
place so I just really want to pay
tribute to Bernadine and just say you
know what you've done over the last six
seven years is quite remarkable and um
by my humble estimation I think you're
one of the best people
um in this sector and I can't tell you
how much I I love you follow your lead
and just look up to you so much so thank
you so much for everything that you're
doing because it's just creating a space
for all of us
um and it means a hell of a lot to a lot
of people so um it really does and um I
don't say this slightly but you're the
best you really are
um and I mean obviously the conference
team is really about how we build this
sense of community and how we kind of
sustain community and
it's it's quite an important thing
because
um you know how one creates their
communities and as people you know just
turn the phrase often used like you know
it's important to find your people but
increasingly that that becomes difficult
and I think it becomes difficult because
there are a couple of things that we um
really orientate from
in higher education in the academy the
society more broadly and I think um
selfishness is one of them
um I think individualism
is one of them and I think that there's
a huge rejection of collectivism and
what's so beautiful about everyone being
here today in the way that they are and
there's people in the crowd there's 136
people online
is this sense of community is this sense
of collectivism and you know I always
think of this idea kind of touching
fingers versus penetrative Fist and I
think what community embodies when we do
it properly is this side of a
penetrative fist and metaphorically
penetrative fist can puncture anything
touching fingers you're going to snap
fingers off if you try and punch through
a brick wall of inequality
but if you have this kind of clench fist
of um collectivism anything is
penetrable and
in terms of how we build communities I
guess what I want us to kind of really
think about
is we're making this cake we're making
this cake and I'm I wouldn't I don't
pretend to be the best cake maker in the
world but we're making this cake and
what we need to think about between a
lot of us
is what ingredients do we want in this
cake now we can have anything at the
moment and to stick on the cake metaphor
the cake we're digesting at the moment
it's kind of leaving us all a little bit
constipated it's not particularly nice
it leaves a horrible aftertaste
and it orientates back to the same thing
the ingredients that make up that cake
are really situated around kind of
selfishness individualism
um an absence of love
in spaces where love is needed now if we
draw on kind of bell hooks's Mantra who
is kind of my my academic hero heroine
um Love is a great axis for us to
spin-off and it's quite a great Jimi
Hendrix what we do want is an axis bold
as love so we've got our access to spin
off we want it to be as bold as we want
it to be so in coming back to this cake
what ingredients do we want our cake in
terms of our communal cake what do we
want in there
or I would humbly suggest or modestly
suggest we need love as an important
part of that
we need this idea of building one a
sense of self but two building a sense
of others and what makes Bernadine so
remarkably unique along with people like
Professor Palmer
and others is that they spend a lot of
their time thinking about how they can
build communities build individuals and
that becomes hugely important because
actually tiny jobs make a mighty ocean
and you know the things that you learn
in those kind of little
um tiny Spates they do end up coming
making this huge big ocean one day that
people can kind of take from
so we've got love as part of this cake
we've got kind of this idea of community
as part of this cake we've got this idea
of pulling the ladder down
so very often I think in this sense of
individualism we pulled ladder up not us
particularly but people can do that so
things about how we pulled a ladder down
they think that becomes hugely important
so in our cake we've got love we've got
community we've got a ladder
um what else do we need to have in there
I think compassion is hugely important
in terms of building that sense of
community and how we construct that and
the types of people we want around us
and empathy so all too often empathy is
disposable believe it or not
when I go to bed I don't sleep so I'm in
something I've never slept to be honest
it's been like this for 20 maybe nearly
20 years and a lot of it is worry so a
lot of it's worry and it's worry about
how much people suffer and it really
really kills me just how much suffering
there is in the world and probably worse
than that how much suffering we can
inflict on one another in our own
communities
so for me it's kind of the one thing we
kind of want to put in this cake is
empathy the thing that we have in the
other cake of individualism is
disposable empathy
so we can see somebody's going through
something and actually we're like oh
next
um
I mean it's bad but it doesn't affect me
well I'm sure sorry for that person but
it doesn't affect me and it's that whole
idea of can we hold someone else's
discomfort can we hold someone else's
pain because part of a community is that
part of the community is holding someone
else's pain someone else's discomfort
and helping them through and as a
collective we can do that
now in terms of kind of thinking about
the last part is cake what would be the
icing on the cake
methodically speaking I guess the icing
would be in some respects is thinking
about
how we Center and create spaces for
people
so how do we create spaces for
the most minoritized so if we think
about higher education in particular
black women women of color but
particularly black women face often very
precarious situations within higher
education and they're left in very
vulnerable situations and we need to
think as a collective what we can do to
continue to mobilize black women and
give them the agencies in those spaces I
think that becomes hugely important and
I guess
we've got to the icing we have this
cherry
and what might the Cherry be and I think
the Cherry is always faith
is always Faith so there's always this
idea of Hope and you know I always think
you know there's an expression that they
use when they say it's the hope that
kills you I disagree with that I think
it's the hope that gives you strength
and it's a hope that gives you belief
that things are getting better
when I first went to this conference
um six or seven years ago and I first
met Bernadine
I'm not a skeptical person but I
remember thinking wow there's a lot of
work to do here I mean I was in Aura
Bernadine in the first place so that was
the first thing and had magnetism and
her
you know the way she's able to bring
people together you know that's not a
that's a really unique
skill really unique skill and she was
able to do this in the space really you
know to try and explain to people how
different things have
have changed or how much things have
mobilized in the last six or seven years
it is quite incredible I always think
people might wake up and think oh well
you know as a generation of people
thinking it's always been like this and
you know it's people you know people
who've been at the Vanguard of this
revolution people like Bernadine who
have created these spaces for people to
be able to now I suppose be in a
situation where you can almost take
things a little bit for granted which is
a good thing by the way we as people of
color as black people are allowed to
take things for granted I mean God knows
we never get to but I always so think
it's very important as my dad always
says the Pioneers never reap the
benefits of their soil
and there are a lot of black women that
create a lot of agency for black and
ethnic minority people to thrive in the
academy and it's also important in terms
of that charity that we put on the cake
that we think about how we can create
spaces for them to thrive
and not only Thrive but also have
periods of rest also find ways to kind
of redistribute the labor and the
responsibility of this work and I think
that becomes hugely important
and I guess you know
when we make anything or break anything
of any note
um what do they always say the proof is
in the pudding
so I guess the proof is in the eating
right and one of the things I kind of
think about is what would this cake
taste like now in my mind in my idyllic
mind is probably a romanticization and a
Melancholy about the fact that it would
probably taste or I like sweet things so
it tastes really sweet it'd be really
nice and
um being an African boy I love Tim milk
evaporated milk so I want to put
evaporated milk on it as well and
um
and in my mind it tastes great it tastes
great but you know cooking on a page and
cooking in practice are always two
completely different things I've never
tasted anything I've never eaten
anything in my eyes on paper that tasted
bad but I have eaten stuff in practice
that tastes horrible now I can theorize
about what would make a good cake but
fundamentally
the proof is in the tasting and the
tasting comes in the practical sense
what are the practical things that we
can do in terms of building that
Community it is so so so important that
you think very carefully about the types
of people you have around you
I was very fortunate to have met
Bernadine I was very fortunate to have
met
um
Professor Donald
um I was very fortunate to learn from
Bernadine learn about the things that
she did and
you know one of the things that was
immensely
um inspiring about burning is that she
did it with this Amazing Grace she does
it with this Amazing Grace and
um you know I think there's about 10
people I would say that are the jewel in
the crown of higher education in the UK
and a place Dr Bernadine as one of them
and the reason being is because that
cake that she looks at in theory on a
page
is something that actually she's able to
do very very well in practice in other
words she can replicate this recipe
at conference one two three four five
and now that I think we're at our sixth
I think so she's been able to replicate
that recipe over and over again now
that's not to take away from anyone
who's able to replicate a recipe over
you know once and be a one-trip pony so
to speak I'm probably one
but
to be able to do it so consistently over
a period of time to be able to build
this community in some respects
you know burning what Bernadine's done
is build the 300 if you've ever seen the
movie the Spartans she's built the 300
you know you've got this huge Empire
that we're going up against in terms of
literally speaking the empire in terms
of you know racism intersectional
inequality discrimination all of those
things
and she's taken this small bowl of
people to take on
um this establishment in some respects
and has done it in the most
effective
um an inclusive way bringing a lot of
people along with her why allies
included and really
I don't know if anything I've said has
made sense
but it's important to kind of emphasize
that this ode really to Bernadine is to
emphasize that when the greatest thing
that I think
people are able to do is to take
something that is very very difficult
and make it look very easy what
berndean's actually been able to do is
build a sense of community and make it
look
very very easy but in reality there's a
lot of things that happen behind the
scenes for her to motivate and to
cultivate this kind of culture for us
all to be privileged to be able to sit
in and I think I think that's important
is thinking about what can we do to
support
other women of color doing this amazing
work like Paulette Williams for example
Dr Chantal Lewis
etc etc who are these types of people
doing this work you know Deb I'm sorry
Dr Deborah and husbands what how can we
support these people
um before I kind of point
the thing the proverbial thing or anyone
I think the first person I've always
look at is myself and I'm by no means
perfect but I I have tried my absolute
best and will continue to do so but I
must say that I've always taken my lead
from the most exceptional black women
that our sector has to offer in society
more broadly so
um I hope that makes some sort of sense
um my whole thing is I never want to
bore people's tears and I'm always more
intrigued to learn from all of you
um and to have a sense of dialogue
because I don't like talking at people I
like talking with people so um it goes
without saying just thank you so so much
for
um
the space I'm so grateful Bernadine I
really do think you're one of the very
very best and um it's not lost on me
um uh I am very very fortunate to be in
the position I'm in but I can I can say
this and I mean this from the bottom of
my heart where there's much love and
sincerity as I could master and thank
you so much for everyone's Support over
all the years
um without any of you I wouldn't have
been able to do it um and if I've
achieved anything of any kind of note
it's really because of all the belief
that you've all had in me and all the
small prayers
um that everyone has said that's kind of
created this Mighty ocean so um I love
you all dearly very much and God bless
and thank you I really appreciate it
thank you Jason
there's a round of applause for you in
the room and we've got 15 minutes for
questions I don't know if you can hear
me I can hear you great yeah okay all
right so for questions
I think we have to use the mic so that
Jason can come here any questions
comments
hello everyone my name is Maureen and
Jason to be honest you just inspired me
um I find your presentation very
beneficial and I was just going to ask
you're a very young person and you've
achieved really this much
what would you say uh the strategies you
had in place that led to your success
even as a as a black uh young man in the
one of the top universities of the world
thank you
oh thank you so so much that's very kind
of you I mean to be honest
um
I I had to write something about two or
three years ago when I first became
professor at Glasgow
um for the Times Higher Education and
they kind of said like you know we
really want to celebrate the fact that
you're at that time the youngest
professor in the UK and um I said to
them to be honest with you there's not
really anything to to celebrate I would
I would say I'm a bit of a cautionary
tale of what not to be so I joke about
this a lot but it's the truth already so
one of my favorite films is Karate Kid
and um Mr Miyagi kind of says good
balance makes good karate and I've said
this to a lot of people before and
metaphorically speaking
I I don't have balance so I've I I've
worked all the hours God sends
and I don't you know it means that life
passes You by and so what I tell people
all the time is that um
yeah I I couldn't have worked any harder
like I couldn't have done any more than
I did
um and I and I pretty much sacrificed
everything in in trying to do in trying
to help as many people as possible not
just myself
um but the thing I would say is that you
need balance and um
I think the most important thing is that
I was working from a position where I
knew that I I wasn't a most gifted
academic I knew I didn't particularly
have um a lot of skill but I I've
mentioned this before I did have the
will and um I was so determined
um and I felt that I needed to dedicate
every second of every single day to try
and Achieve something and also my mum
had sacrificed so many years looking
after me that I wanted to show her that
you know I can't give her those years
back but by trying my best that's the
only way I can show her that I It met
you know I'm so grateful everything she
did so the advice I would give to
people in the academy
is that balance is really important you
know um self-care is really really
important I'm terrible at that
um and the thing that I would also
mention is that um
most people I meet in terms of black
people their level of skill is so
exceptional I can't even comprehend it
and the one thing that they need to have
to complement that which most people
also often have in terms of black people
is the will and if you're blessed enough
to have those two things which to be
quite honest with you most black people
I've met in the academy do have then
this guy should be the limit my job in
the position that I've been in and that
I continue to be in is to make sure that
that playing field
is as level as possible so that when
black people paid Afraid on everything
they need to do when their opportunity
comes they're not denied it because of
their race they're not denied it because
their gender or any other in sectional
variable that's levied up black and
black and ethnic minority people they
get it on Merit and so that's that's
what I I'm trying to do
um and
I my job is to try and Achieve that I
try and keep trying but I think the most
important thing is that um
black people are so exceptional and I
always I guess I always knew that the
only person I probably never thought
about myself ironically was me I didn't
think I was particularly exceptional and
I still don't but um I think the most
important thing is also hope and and and
faith and it's about
you know sometimes people say how badly
they want something but you know you've
it always comes down to what would you
be willing to sacrifice and I think
there's a balance in that
um for me I am I I think maybe the cost
was too much
um
but then the other side of it is that um
I also feel like I've been very very
privileged to have helped a lot of
people and someone said to me would I
have done it differently I wouldn't do
it differently but that doesn't mean I
would advise someone to do what I've
done because
um this isn't everything there are a lot
more important things in life and the
easiest way to explain that is that my
daughter is 17. and I really don't know
where the time went
um and she was sat here right now she
turned around if you asked her what do
you think of my dad what do you think
your dad she'd say it was awesome if you
said do you think Dad's always present
he'd say he is present but he's not
present if that makes sense
and it's things like that where you
think if I could do it all over again
like I just don't understand why the 17
years went you know and you know my
younger one it's different but that's
what I mean violence is very important
and you know
I I mean this with all in all sincerity
this isn't everything you know but um
what is everything is having that
balance but also managing that ambition
alongside it and if you put those two
things together really well not only
will you get to the top but you'll be
really really happy inside if that makes
sense and sometimes I'm not always happy
because I look at the inequality and it
gets me down because I feel they should
be there are a lot more exceptional
people than me and they should be in
position I'm in
um and so that gets me down but it makes
me also realize I've got a lot more work
to do to make sure that this doesn't
become something that always I don't
want to be the only person I never did
um and that's
that's the thing that's always driven me
thank you Jason and we've got a question
online
um Joanna would you like to ask a
question
and unmute yourself
or you can just type it in the chat and
we'll relay it for you all right that's
great
well we wait for Joanna are there any
more questions in the room
yeah
like Andy said I'm getting my steps in
okay thank you very much for
oh
thank you very much for the opportunity
um thank you so much for the lecture
Justin and Bernardin for this platform
yeah I I just looked you up online I saw
that um he couldn't speak until you're
11 years old
and um I mean in a space of less than 25
years you've done so much for yourself
what was that um and and this is to some
people some teachers have probably told
them oh you can't be this you can't get
to this because you have this how are
you able to surmount that challenge how
are you able to
speak to yourself to get yourself out of
that stereotype and to achieve them
great things
uh Jonah thank you so much um to be
honest I can
I was very fortunate to have the mother
I did and the father I did but
particularly my mother I was very very
fortunate to have um 150 yard day
um I'm very very lucky that um that she
chose me to be her son and
or God chose her to be my mother should
I say
um and
and I and I had and I had a teacher at
College
um Sandra who massively
in you know he changed my mentality when
I was 18 but I think the biggest thing
was that um
I I genuinely I genuinely don't
believe there's nothing I can't not do
um
because I I I I I
think I'm willing to suffer a big part
of it is how much are you willing to
suffer and I think I was always good at
that because I'm so good at losing I
lost so much in my life but um I was
always able to lose with exceptional
Grace which which meant that when I won
occasionally I could be a good winner
um and I knew what it felt like to lose
but I think the biggest thing was that
um
I just
I just I just wouldn't give in
um and
I always had this
I think look I could give you 101
answers but if I'm just going to be
absolutely honest with you I I don't
know how useful this answer will be to
you but
I I I I think it's Destiny I really do I
there is no explanation I can give I've
had
so many people ask me this question and
the only thing I can really um
say it's his Destiny you know and I'm
just very fortunate that um
like God decided that he'd smile down on
me I
I just think maybe I was destined to be
in this situation
um because like I said there are people
far more capable
um a lot more gifted than I'll ever be
and for some reason I think there's some
aspect of Fate to it and um
and I also I I work
Ed really I gave it everything I had um
and the probably the more important
aspect of that is that everything I had
I gave away I I shared as much as I
could with people I helped as many
people as I could and and maybe the good
Lord saw it upon himself to to bless me
because of the things I'd been fortunate
enough to maybe do for other people
I'd love to tell you there was some
scientific or pragmatic or positivist
answer but there really there really
isn't I I just think that it was fate
and I got very fortunate to have the
mother that I did
okay this is Tony thank you so much for
sharing with us you're truly an
inspiration
metaphor I love metaphors by the way
thank you for that thank you um your
cake metaphor
what would be the oven
in your cake metaphor what would be the
oven that is such a great question what
would be the oven well it definitely is
in the academy uh who
funnily enough
funnily enough I think the oven
and I'm saying this in front of friends
so I hope it's taken as such I think the
oven could be built all the oven could
be metaphorically speaking it could be
more men of color
I think we can do more
in my opinion
um that's you know
I think
white allies can always do more it goes
without saying but in terms of thinking
about responsibility and accountability
I think men of color can do more and I
think that oven
um you know because fundamentally it's
always Grandma's hands that it's kind of
doing the building and the lifting and
the mobilizing to kind of quote bill
with us but
I I think the oven could be
um Mena color doing more
um that that's you know structurally I
think what the oven could be and I think
that we're beginning to see that in kind
of small tenants but I think there needs
to be a collective action
amongst men of color in the academy to
really think about how they bake that
cake
and you know if we're going to talk
about it being metaphorical that cake is
the mobilization of black women in the
same way historically black women have
always mobilized
black men and men of color and women of
color have also done the same and I
think that's hugely important
thank you
[Music]
no answered my question in a different
ways so sorry
uh I think you somehow answered my
question in a different way
um I want to ask like it is easier to
build or like influence right once you
come to a position of power like
position of influence
um so do you like way to Lou achieve
that position or like how do you
navigate while those are advancing and
career and also while influencing and
building communities I know it's a very
difficult question and you also talk
about sacrifice and also like um
um like how much do you sacrifice so
yeah no it's a great question I know I
guess you're asking a relation to myself
so I can only speak for myself but um
that there are a couple of people on on
this call maybe
um that might know me
um and I've worked in higher education
for just over 10 years
um and I mean if I can be candid I never
waited until now
um to do it uh I I did it when I first
came in and the reason I did is because
actually
I they always say you should never meet
your Heroes and I saw a lot of examples
of what I didn't want to be
unfortunately so again those kind of
horrible ingredients of individualism
you know selfishness and all those kind
of things I didn't want to be that but
that was the only thing I observed when
it came to higher education so you know
you'd ask people for help and no one
would really help you so it then made me
think about what I don't want to be and
what I'm going to try and do differently
and so I was always I always help people
from the very beginning and anyone that
knows me or has known me over the last
six or seven plus years I think could
say that
um and I don't talk about everything I
do for you know because that's not the
point that's not the purpose of helping
people but I've always done it
um and and I guess as the stakes have
got higher and higher you maybe have
more resources so you can do more and
more and more and this is probably the
most resources I've maybe ever had to be
able to do that so I can it's really a
continuation of my my my mission from
when I first started 10 years ago and
that mission was born out of the fact
that there wasn't actually anyone that I
saw that was really engaging in that
sense of collectivism and community that
we also cherish now in terms of what
Bernadine has done here today and has
done for many years so that was a big
thing and I guess
you only really know
how committed you are to these things
when things start changing and the more
opportunities you've got so one of the
things that was said to me very often is
that if I become more selfish I could
progress very very quickly and I
rejected that I rejected that I never
did it and I honestly believe if I had
been like that I don't think I'd be in a
position I'm in now and I think the
sense of kind of well-being and
protecting oneself is always a difficult
thing because
um there's a cost to everything and I
think the most important way you can
kind of Levy that cost is to try and
distribute or have a collective you know
that Collective responsibility helps in
ensuring that the burden doesn't fall on
you know the few and that's why I think
it's important for all of us you know in
this space particularly as I've
mentioned today men of color and white
people in particular to
um
lift as much of that burden as possible
so that the burden's evenly distributed
and I think that's how one is able to
sustain himself
um when that sense of collectivism isn't
there it falls on a couple of people and
the weight of that burden is crushing
and that's and I guess like um that's
the thing that can be difficult and in
my own context you know I I I do feel a
huge sense of pressure because I think
because of the way I've done it there's
been a huge weight of expectation for
many many years because people clemency
is a nice person that helps everyone and
so you never say no and I guess it has
consequent a knock-on effect on other
things which is why I always say I'm a
cautionary tale and that's not to say
not to help people it's just to say that
um if we all chip in it makes it easier
that it doesn't fall on the few of us it
falls on all of us to do that you know
and and I I hope that makes some sort of
sense
hello everyone
my name is Google
I'm a PhD student in the University of
Leeds um
thank you very much Professor Jason your
uh
very
huge source of inspiration
thank you yeah
um but
I've heard what you said about
um sacrifice sacrifice right
um
we've been told that
people who have achieved great things
you know actually sacrifice a lot
or in Academia
um what I want to ask you specifically
is the fact that
you did your masters
you did your PhD and you're not a
professor under a short period of time
how did you do that because you know for
me
it's important to learn
um I want to be an academic but
most times when I listen to stories I
become scared will I ever become an
academic especially when one has you
know um been in the industry for a long
time
so how were you able to do it I know you
need to do publish a lot of articles
and what are those sacrifices
specifically that you made to be able to
get to where you are because I mean it
is different for everyone but stories
like yours
can't help someone like me to begin to
pencil down how to program myself to be
able to get to where you are
as a mentor mentoring must not be when I
engage you personally mentoring is
in
a space like this like Bernadine has
provided so Mentor me I'm probably some
other people in a short period of time
now thank you no that's great I thank
you so much I mean the first thing is
that um you can't become an academic and
you're a lot more exceptional and I'll
never be
um okay so that that's just remember
that um and
how did I do it um
I mean look what I'm going to tell you
is not something I genuinely I wouldn't
recommend somebody to do this but I
for like 15 years maybe longer I didn't
sleep okay so I was a pea teacher so I
didn't train and I was going to train
sociology so I I don't have a degree in
sociology none of them believe it or not
so I I taught myself at night
um
and I basically made the decision that I
don't have
the same academic gifts that most people
have but I I do have this will to
succeed but I needed to um
I needed to take up every single inch
possible to convert as many meters in my
favor as possible
and so I read I learned I studied I did
it obsessively
um and I think for 15 years I wrote 500
Words a day on anything just so I could
improve my writing
um but the biggest thing was is
um I was I was dedicated
um and an obsessive I was really really
obsessive which is why when I say like
you know
there are aspects of my behavior that I
wouldn't in all good faith and
Consciousness I'd advise someone to be
but I did really want to be an academic
um and I knew that from the position I
was starting from was going to be very
difficult but I set some really clear
goals and I think some people are goals
focused and goals orientated
um I I am quite goals orientated
um but my goals are selfless they're not
goals that are so much associated with
myself so it's always been about wanting
to help people and I knew that the
harder I worked the more I could do to
help people and so because my um
my my intrinsic motivation was always
altruistic I always wanted to help as
many people as possible and I just kind
of surmised that if I worked as hard as
I could I would get into more elevated
positions where I could do that so it
goes without saying every person works
hard I mean
particularly if you're an ethnic
minority in British Academia but the
thing I would say is to have a clear set
of goals and to manifest them and
you know it's been well documented now
but I I said you know I was decorating
my my mum's bedroom wall my younger
brother and I wrote three goals on this
Post-it
in one of them and the final goal on the
post it was um I I wanted to one day
work at Oxford Cambridge now to give you
some context when I wrote that in 2012 I
was still teaching PE in school
so I'm still a school teacher teaching
PE in school so I think
you know pointing those goals up and
having something to work towards is
really important and then it's kind of
really about strategy and being really
strategic so how are you going to do
that and one of the things I learned I
learned of observing people because in
Academia if there's five directions to
the station people tend to give you two
and then they say when you get to the
end of the road ask somebody for
directions to the station the truth is
everybody knows what the secrets are
it's just that because it's so horribly
horribly individualistic egotistic
selfish and competitive no one ever
gives you
all of the details you know they always
miss a few out and I guess the details
that I would tell you is that you always
need to think about right I need to be
strategic in terms of where I publish I
need to think about um the types of jobs
that I go for I need to think about what
I'm doing that's slightly different and
I need to look at Job specs and make
sure that every aspect of my CV is
tailored towards that and I also need to
be ambitious and
every black person I've met in Academia
is ambitious and every person comment I
can do is ambitious but it's about
there's a difference between ambition
and then kind of unapologetically going
for it and the Unapologetic part of it
is the abandonment of imposter syndrome
so my belief is that I don't believe in
imposter syndrome because I believe that
you you are all where you're supposed to
be you're all you are all great beyond
measure and you always are supposed to
be that's not an accident that didn't
happen by accident it happens because
you're blessed and you're great and you
really have to walk into that and be
Unapologetic about what you want to do
so if you say right now go go that I
want to be
a professor five years from now
then you go for it but you have these
ingredients in place about how you're
going to construct this wonderful cake
and be really really focused
around how you're going to do that
whilst engaging in self-care because
that's what I didn't do is also why when
gray really young I think
um but I I strongly believe that and if
there's one thing that I say that if you
remember anything that I say I really do
believe in abandoning imposter syndrome
is the greatest gift you can give to
yourself wherever you are for a PhD
student at the moment at University of
Leeds one of the best universities in
the world you're there because you're
the best you're dead because you're one
of the best so that's something you
always you need to hold on to you're not
there by accident you you will know the
cost of everything you've done to get to
this point now and I know it sounds
crazy to say but you're really not far
off you're really not far off you just
got to hang in there and be really
Unapologetic about what you're going to
do from here on in and say to yourself
like this is where I'm supposed to be
none of this like I'll
you know I sometimes I feel like I don't
make no no like um
if there's one thing I do know I don't
know a lot but if there's one thing I do
know is that black people and people of
color more generally are truly
exceptional and there is no mountain
they cannot overcome and I'm telling you
in three or four years time maybe sooner
than that you'll be headlining this bill
and you'll be giving the same advice to
someone else and
um I honestly believe that with all of
my heart
thank you Jason there's one question
online and then there's another question
down there and then I think we'll have
to wrap it up unfortunately
so this question is from Marlo delara
um you've touched a bit on this already
but
he says I find it difficult in Academia
when working with with other people of
the global majority and they don't have
the same attitude towards a collective
mentality
in practice it can reinforce oppression
Olympics incentives harmful hierarchies
do you sense a shift in Academia of
tending to one another as opposed to
leaving others behind
and do you uh do you propose calling
them in or how do we acknowledge these
harmful behaviors amongst black and
brown academics in the community it's
heartbreaking
that's a great great question and um I
have to admit that is the thing that
kills me more than anything and that's
unfortunately that was my experience
when I first came into Academia you know
a lot of these people that I'd I kind of
looked up to
um if I'm being honest it was very
disappointing when I met them and I saw
but actually what they said there was a
huge disconnect the practice element
there was a huge disconnect between
their theories and what they said and
what they actually did and you know I
always go back to this Maya Angelou
quote it's about how you made people
feel and you know I feel like none of
these people they were it was a sad
realization to see that they were all in
it for themselves which by the way I
don't begrudge them and switch to their
own but I think if you say one thing and
you do something completely different
they think it creates a juxtaposition
and a hypocrisy that's quite hard to
digest
um and and I found that difficult
um as you get older
you learn more some of the reasons why
people do that and you probably become
slightly less judgmental of that but I
still think that um
I think things have changed if I'm being
honest like I said I've spoken about it
many times like but people like
Bernadine
like Paula you know people like Chantal
you know the amazing work Donald does
across several kind of uh institutions
in society and in the academy
um has been has been hugely integral to
changing how people think about these
things
um and I do think things are changing I
think there is more of a collective fist
now you know you've got
more and more people thinking in ways to
protect one another and I think in such
divisive and
fractious times never has it been more
important for us to stay together you
know
um drawing on Al Green like this is the
most important time let's let's stay
together like we all win in the end
but the end in terms of where the line
is can be determined by us the better we
stay together as a collective the sooner
the Finishing Line will come but if it
stays as sporadic as it is it becomes
more difficult and that that finish line
just moves further and further away now
we will win believe me but but we we are
the ones ultimately that will determine
when we win and I think the more we stay
together the sooner the Finish Line will
come and I think that's hugely important
and I think we have to protect that as
much as possible we really really have
to protect
collectivism
um love
um faith and looking out for one another
it's so so important and I think that um
you know the compassion and love that we
need to have for one another is the
thing that's going to steer us through
these really difficult times and it's
why I always try and talk about it any
opportunity I get because my faith in
human beings despite some of the
horrible things that happen in this
world has never been unshaken I think
human beings are capable of great things
and I think that they're capable of
amazing and beautiful things that kind
of uplift people and we just need to
keep that our core if we can keep that
at our core we're going to win this
thing we're going to win this thing I
just know it
thank you
good afternoon
this will not make sense but I'm looking
at what you said about a a minus color
being part of this because I'm thinking
that we are thinking we are taking it
many different levels because it starts
from even raising HR
sorry say that again I didn't quite hear
it I'm so sorry
I don't know which part you had
I heard raising a child
okay
I think he's taking it a step back
because it's about even raising a child
of color what that means so it feels
like sometimes in these institutions we
are dealing with trying to raise some
people's children because they are
dealing with a package of growing up
like that so now we are trying to fight
our own War as women and black women and
women of color but part of that involves
raising the kids that other parents
couldn't raise and then we have to deal
with that in all our careers
that's such a great Point thank you so
much and I guess the story element of
that there's a tax on that there is
attacks on black women in terms of their
emotionality their psychological State
um their physical well-being you know
and I think it is incumbent you know we
all have a sense of agency it's
incumbent
um on people
men of color white women you know white
men any of the above to do that work on
themselves so that work isn't always
left to black women to do
uh you know I can't emphasize this
enough I was very very fortunate to have
the mother that I did
um that taught me things that I probably
didn't apprec I appreciated it when I
was younger but it's something that's
held me in very good stead
um now I'm an adult because they're just
things you learn you know I you take it
for granted being read you know black
feminist literature from a very young
age even though I don't know what mum
was talking about there was books all
around the house you know he went to a
lot of things me and my brothers around
that that really kind of place an
emphasis on what we need to do as men of
color to support black women and you
know those lessons that I had 25 years
ago you know I really kind of cradled a
lot of my thinking to this point now and
I think the points you make are so so
true and I can only speak for myself
that I'll continue to do work on myself
so that I can be a better service and
support and uplift
um black women and women of color more
generally